The Buddha often compared the sense
fields with the ocean and the dangerous
creatures living in it. I was wondering
if you could shed some light on that
analogy since I myself can't really make
much sense of it. Uh Uh
Yeah, so the ocean
the ocean
stands for
something whose depth
or whose um
extent you cannot fathom. Like it's
you you can get only guess
how far it goes
and what things it can it can contain.
So in the same way
um
you have no
way to anticipate how how much your
senses can pressure you.
How much how how much um
how many different significances they
can try to overwhelm you with.
How many sight, sound, smells, tastes,
and touches can strike those senses.
Um so in the same way it's the the the
in the same way as you you wouldn't
you you couldn't possibly deal with the
ocean because again, you don't know the extent
because again, you don't know the extent
of it. You couldn't deal with it fully
by taking all of the individual things
and uh
having countermeasures against them. You
need to
uh
you need to be prepared for anything
that might come within the ocean.
And the same way
you need to be prepared for anything
that could come within your six sense
bases. It doesn't matter how coarse, how subtle
It doesn't matter how coarse, how subtle
How
um
pleasant, unpleasant.
Um
how familiar or unfamiliar.
familiar or unfamiliar.
All of it has to be included in the same
training. And all of it has to be permeated by the
And all of it has to be permeated by the
same immovability.
So, oftentimes
oftentimes
people overlook that, of course, because
their practice revolves around
dealing with specific things. So, like
whatever uh
uh
person that upsets them or such
situation that's challenging them,
they will try to
uh
do these kind of reframing techniques
that sometimes are
um
presented as meta or whatever, even
though they're not,
to sort of
tackle those specific situations, those
specific people, and not suffer any kind
of them anymore.
And that's why that approach can never the
that's why that approach can never the
the simile of the ocean uh
shows you why that approach can never
work. It can never uh contribute to actual
It can never uh contribute to actual
liberation cuz
what what does it matter
if you learn how to deal with crocodiles
if the sharks can still get you.
Uh so, there's always going to be a
different type of
type of
challenging experience that you've never
seen before
that you have that you have no
uh
no no means to reframe in that way.
And then craving will arise.
You will get overwhelmed in that
situation because you didn't develop
yourself in regard to the whole thing.
So, uh
uh
of course, you can only experience one
thing at a time, really. Like, you can't
uh
simultaneously experience
everything. Even in your whole life, uh you will not
Even in your whole life, uh you will not
have experienced anything that you
that was possible to experience.
But you certainly can
hold yourself back
from being concerned with these
specifics. And then
And then
noticing this inherent uncertainty
first of all, that exists with in regard
to your sense bases. Like I don't know
what I could be hit with.
Maintain that recognition so that you
don't get
bogged down on any specific sense
objects. And then see
And then see
that already arouses a sense of
a certain pressure.
So that keeps you on guard.
So that when there when there isn't
anything acutely pressuring you
with the six sense bases,
you still know
this whole domain
in itself is
liable to attack in a way that I can't
even um
um
I can't even anticipate, basically.
And then that recognition
letting that sink in
is how you train yourself in regard to
the whole extent of it. So that nothing
then that could come through there would
be a surprise.
Whereas what people you would usually do
is
if what's currently present is is not uh unpleasant enough,
unpleasant enough,
if it's fine,
then that's it. Like
you let your guard down and
you just rest in that until something
comes up and then you're overwhelmed. So
So
that's what it that also is is
another way of saying that is not
finding safety
in whatever current circumstance of
your experience cuz that's what the six
six sense bases are.
Whatever current circumstance of your
experience you find yourself in
you remember
this whole domain
has sharks, monsters,
crocodiles. They might They may not be here right
They might They may not be here right
now.
But it's similar to you know you you
when you're floating in the ocean, it's
not like
the sharks come for you immediately, but
they could.
So
maintaining that recognition then
is training you training your mind
to give up that passion that it has for
these six sense bases that it sees them
as
a place for
getting pleasure.
Which you know there is some pleasure to
be found.
And the reason why people are infatuated
with it is because they don't see it
also comes with all these threats.
That you can't divorce from the
pleasure. Simply by being in the water
Simply by being in the water
those threats are also possible. So it's a
it's a simile that you know yeah that
the whole the sutra as a whole
I think is quite often overlooked
overlooked. Also the way it says
Also the way it says
that the way you um
cross over the ocean or you liberate
yourself essentially is to withstand the
tides.
So when it says
the the eyes, the ear
the eyes, the ear
the nose, their tides is sight, sound,
smells, tastes, and touches.
And then withstanding those tides is how
you free yourself. He's basically saying
you can't change the fact that certain
sights or sounds or sense objects have a
a force, let's say, or a or a pressure
that they exert.
And again, that's something that people
would usually be trying to deal with.
Prevent those pressures from arising. But
But
the problem is not the pressure arises.
The problem is when you haven't trained
yourself you haven't trained your mind
you haven't trained your mind
as I described before to see those six
sense bases for what they are as a as a
not something to rest on, not something
to
to to feel that you can
feel that you can be safe by
manipulating it. Uh then
Uh then
you can't withstand it.
Like when those things come up, when
when certain that force of certain sense
objects come up comes up
immediately you are pulled to the
prospect of doing something about it.
So, if it's pleasure, chasing after it.
Displeasure, pushing it away.
Uh
and that's how you fail to withstand it.
So, the tide will still be there when
you train yourself.
Uh once you have trained yourself, the
tide will still be there. But
this impulse to
deal with the
uh
well, go towards the pleasure or deal
with the pain, get rid of it, basically.
That's what fades.
So, it's not the tide that goes away.
It's your response to it.
That came from not being able to
withstand it.
That's what subsides.
And it's not a decision that you just
cuz it could sound like that like oh you
just make this firm determination to
stand still but no that comes from an
understanding. It comes from understanding those six
It comes from understanding those six
sense bases
as not a basis for safety because
if you understand it that way
then like
like
you basically realize however
safe or however comfortable I can make
this in the moment
there are still all these threats
waiting for me
that might come at any time.
Then how could you possibly have
an impulse to
kind of
or or following a promise that like you
you you might be able to sort it out and
and make it fine.
You just give up on that whole project
and that's the liberation.